Therese Weil Lansburgh papers SSC.MS.00090
Sophia Smith Collection
Therese Weil Lansburgh papers
1962-1994
Sophia Smith Collection
Lansburgh, Therese Weil,
SSC.MS.00090
2.417 linear feet (6 containers)
Therese Weil Lansburgh was a social worker, children's welfare advocate and lobbyist. This colection includes her personal and professional papers documenting Lansburgh's career as a social worker and champion for the rights of children, and particularly for affordable day care and social service organizations in which she was involved.
Biographical / Historical
Therese Weil Lansburgh received an A.B. from Smith College in 1940. She went on to earn a M.S.W. from the Tulane University School of Social Work, circa 1942. From 1943-1945 she was a case worker with the American Red Cross in Boston, Massachusetts, and from 1947-1949 was a visiting teacher in Columbus, Mississippi, where she started that state's first class for mentally disabled children. She worked as a social worker for the Children's Guild in Baltimore, Maryland from 1959-1961, and from 1963-1965 as a caseworker for the Department of Mental Hygiene in Glen Burnie, Maryland. From 1967-1971, she was president of the Day Care and Child Development Council of America. In 1970, Lansburgh served as vice-chairman of the Developmental Child Care Forum of the White House Conference on Children. The recommendations of the Forum were the basis of the Child Development Act of 1971, which was passed by Congress but vetoed by President Richard M. Nixon. From 1983-1987, Lansburgh served as Director of Education and Public Policy at the Regional Center for Infants and Young Children in Rockville, Maryland.
Throughout her long career, Lansburgh championed the rights and interests of children, particularly in her work to force affordable day care onto the national agenda. She worked tirelessly as a volunteer and board member for a broad range of state and national children's agencies. Lansburgh wrote prolifically about day care and delivered numerous speeches on the subject. Her resume boasts a long list of honors and awards for her work. Therese Weil Lansburgh died September 2002. She is survived by her daughter, Deborah (Wolff) Adler and son, Randolph Wolff.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes personal and professional papers documenting Therese Weil Lansburgh's career as a social worker and champion for the rights of children, especially for affordable day care. Types of materials include biographical and financial records; personal and professional correspondence; writings and speeches; and material pertaining to many of the social service organizations in which Lansburgh was involved.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open to research use according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Therese Weil Lansburgh.
Child care--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Child welfare--Maryland--History--20th century--Sources; Child welfare--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Day care centers--Law and legislation--United States--History--Sources; Social work with children--United States--History--Sources; Social workers--United States--History--Sources; Organization files; Programs; Family social work--United States--History-Sources; Financial records; Writings; memorabilia; Speeches.; correspondence; Lansburgh, Therese Weil
- Series I. BIOGRAPHICAL AND CORRESPONDENCE
  - Curriculum Vitae (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with the Sophia Smith Collection, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Charities, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal correspondence, 1964-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4, 7-19)
  - Menus, invitations, thank you notes, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorabilia, 1962-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Professional correspondence (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Series II. WRITINGS
  - Child Care: A Comprehensive Guide by Steveanne Auerbach, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Child Care: A Comprehensive Guide by Steveanne Auerbach, 1965-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Compensatory Education, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Testimony for the Dewberry Commission, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters to newspapers (Box 2, Box 7)
  - Penny Wise and Pound Foolish, chapter 2, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Human Revolution, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Writings for the Maryland Committee for Children and Youth, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III. ORGANIZATIONS AND PUBLICATIONS
  - Advisory Council on Child Welfare, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The American Parents Committee – Washington Report, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Baltimore County Welfare Board, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Behavior Today, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Child Day Care Association, Inc. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Child Study Association of Maryland, Inc., 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Child Welfare League of America, Inc., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Children's Lobby (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Day Care and Child Development Council of America, Inc.
    - Reports (incomplete), 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous materials (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "The Expansion of Day Care in Chicago" by the Bank Street College of Education, NY, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Day Care Council of New York, Inc.
    - United Neighborhood House, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Governor's Commission on the Status of Women, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Head Start (Dr. Littlefield), 1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - HEW News: A Guide for Planning and Operating Home-Based Child Development Programs, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - The Hogg Foundation for Mental Health, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - League of Women Voters of Maryland, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Maryland Association for Mental Health, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Maryland Association for Mental Health, 1972-1977 (Box 3A, Folder 1-3)
    - Maryland Committee for Children and Youth, 1971 (Box 3A, Folder 4)
    - Maryland Department of Public Welfare, 1965-1967 (Box 3A, Folder 5)
  - Maryland Committee for Day Care of Children
    - Doings in Day Care, 1964-1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to members, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - News releases and information sheets, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Programs and events, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Board of Directors: minutes and reports, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Executive committee, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Miscellaneous: committees and lists, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Nominating Committee, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Public Policy Committee, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Planning Committee, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Notes for newsletter, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Maryland Conference of Social Concern, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Maryland Department of Health and Public Welfare, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Maryland Food Committee, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous Publications and programs, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - National Commission for the Day Care of Children
    - Executive Board: minutes and reports, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Chapter Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Membership Committee, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Newsletters, 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - National Council of Organizations for Children and Youth
    - Newsletters, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Focus on Youth and Children, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of America (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Regional Planning Council, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Report on Preschool Education (incomplete), 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - The Richmond Fellowship of America, 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Today, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - United Neighborhood Houses legislative bulletin, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Washington Bulletin, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Washington Watch, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Series IV. MISCELLANEOUS
  - Child Care Services Act, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Economic Opportunity Amendments, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Child Care Centers and Services Act, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Comprehensive Head Start, Child Development and Family Services Act, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Child Development and Family Services Bill, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous re: legislation on child day care, 1972-1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Joyce Haddon, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Hand-sewn dolls, children's folk noisemakers, pins and other memorabilia, 1973; undated (Box 5, Folder 9)